so can a lay lifestyle lead to becoming
an arahant a lay life still no
no that's impossible the off the
question yeah that's often
often asked is can a layman be an
arahant but that depends what's meant by laymen
but that depends what's meant by laymen
if you mean that somebody
is not formally ordained doesn't wear
robes then yes a layman can become another
then yes a layman can become another
hunt but if by laymen you mean
partaking in the lifestyle of laymen
living in company
still having concerns with the world
living a household life
not being sense restrained that's
impossible so from that point of view layman cannot
so from that point of view layman cannot
be another hunt that's when the suit is
a
layman as in a person not ordained in
the big order
but became an arahant he wasn't a
householder who became another hand he
was a person who wasn't ordained but
wasn't living as a householder
either so the most famous case is bahia
who who himself was a a naked a woodback
ascetic he was just waiting woodback to cover
he was just waiting woodback to cover
himself and he was living very
austerely mindfully practicing for who
knows how long and
he was so pure that he himself thought
he is full enlightened
and then the devout of compassion said
no actually not for enlightened go and
meet the buddha
and that's the famous instruction where
the buddha all he needed to say to him
was in the scene let there just be the
scene in the herd let's
let there just be the hurt and so on for
all the senses and he became another
so technically he was a layman he wasn't
he wasn't a monk he wasn't in the den
because then he asked the buddha
oh can i join your order he said yeah go
and find the ball and the rope
uh but then you got killed by a cow
so so technically he was a layman who
became another hunt
but you realize he was far from living a
layman's life he was basically
a type of summon an ascetic just not
ordained in the order and often that that's
in the order and often that that's
that's where the lions get blurred
people say oh so you don't need to be a
monk as in you don't need to be formally
as in you don't need to be formally
ordained to become an arahant
means i can live a household life and
become another hunt no
you need to live like a monk whether you
wear robes and you're ordained formally
or not that doesn't matter
but the lifestyle of somebody who has
renounced the world
with sense restraint well that matters
that is a necessary basis for it
what does constitute a summoner sense
restraint celibacy
seclusion devoted to seclusion as much
as possible
and not being engaged preoccupied
concerned inspired by worldly affairs
inspired by worldly affairs
so you might need to do some worldly
things to some extent
even as monks you have to but uh
that's one thing doing it as a like a
chore and doing it because you're still
driven by it and you still want it and
you sort of desire towards it
so that that must be abandoned so
technically you can live
a lay life but
if you were able to live lay life yet be
so withdrawn from everything
succeed in that why don't you just
become a monk nothing would stop you
from becoming a monk
so usually when somebody doesn't become
monkeys because
something is still stopping them in the
world which is a form of concern and
that in itself
is an impediment for if they want to be
an arab
so one can go forth without ordaining
yes but not because you feel like you've
gone forth but because you actually
became so dependent or higher
and that's why the noble arya sangha in
the suttas
includes lay people they were not monks
but they were actually aryas
and consequently one can go forth and
ordain and still be a householder in his mind
and still be a householder in his mind
so wearing robes is not a guarantee that
you will
that you are that you have that
distinction of a noble sangha